<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true declaration of the arriuall of Cornelius Haga (with others that accompanied him) ambassadour for the generall states of the vnited Netherlands, at the great citie of Constantinople. Together with the entertainement vnto them giuen, by the Turke, when they came to his palace, and what priuiledges were by him granted vnto the said vnited Prouinces. And also, the copie of certaine letters, sent vnto the said states of the Netherlands, from Constantinople. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 838:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true declaration of the arriuall of Cornelius Haga (with others that accompanied him) ambassadour for the generall states of the vnited Netherlands, at the great citie of Constantinople. Together with the entertainement vnto them giuen, by the Turke, when they came to his palace, and what priuiledges were by him granted vnto the said vnited Prouinces. And also, the copie of certaine letters, sent vnto the said states of the Netherlands, from Constantinople. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for Thomas Archer, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes-head-Palace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Haga, Cornelis, 1578-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Turkey --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE DECLARATION of the arriuall of <hi>Cornelius Haga,</hi> (with others that accompanied him) Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour <hi>for the generall States of the vnited Netherlands,</hi> at the great Citie of CONSTANTINOPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER WITH</hi> the Entertainement vnto them giuen, by the <hi>Turke, when they came to his Palace, and</hi> what Priuiledges were by him granted vnto the ſaid vnited Prouinces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND ALSO,</hi> The Copie of certaine Letters, ſent vnto the <hi>ſaid States of the Netherlands, from</hi> Conſtantinople.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the</hi> Dutch <hi>Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in <hi>Popes-head-Palace.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18145:2"/>
            <p>Winter) and hauing paſt them, at laſt after he had trauelled ſixe Moneths together, he arriued ſafely at <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Where, vpon the firſt day of <hi>May, 1612</hi> he had audience giuen him by the great Emperour of the Turkes, to the great honour and reputation of the <hi>Netherland</hi> Prouinces; and of the States ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the ſame: The Solemnitie whereof was in this manner performed.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadour was conuayed vnto the great Turkes Court by <hi>Saphiler Aga,</hi> the chiefe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all the Turkes Horſe-men: and <hi>Siaus Baſſa,</hi> principall of all the Gentlemen in the Turkes Court; accompanied with an hundred <hi>Siauſers</hi> all on Horſe-backe, in ſuch and the ſame manner, as they vſe to fetch and conuay the Ambaſſadours of the greateſt Monarches and Kings that are, vnto his Court. The Ambaſſadour hauing encreaſed his Traine with ſome Netherlanders as then reſident in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> by reaſon that at the ſame time, there lay diuers Netherland-ſhips before the towne: and beſides them, with ſome that were his good friends, both inhabitants, and others of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whom he before had knowne: whereby the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> was preſerued, to the great contentment not onely of the Turke himſelfe, but alſo of all the <hi>Baſſas</hi> of his Court.</p>
            <p>The olde Captaine <hi>Baſſa,</hi> for a ſigne and token of great affection and honour, cauſed the Ambaſſadour to ride vpon his owne beſt Horſe, which was moſt ſumptuouſly ſadled &amp; brideled, wherin the Turkes, aboue all other Nations, doe ſpecially ſhew their pride &amp; power. And ſo in great ſolemnitie the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Siauſers,</hi> or the great Turkes Gentlemen, richly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18145:2"/> clad and apparelled in Caſſockes of cloath of Gold, Veluet, and Sattin, tode two and two before him: after them followed their Seruants, and ſome <hi>Ianit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> afoote, with two <hi>Dragomans,</hi> or Interpreters, on horſe-backe: after them followed the Ambaſſadour, accompanied on each ſide, by the afore-ſaid <hi>Saphiler Aga,</hi> and <hi>Siaus Baſſa,</hi> and his owne followers, who as Gentlemen, (after the manner there) doe alſo kiſſe the great Turkes hand, and in that manner rode with a great applauſe and concourſe of people to the <hi>Serralio,</hi> or Palace of the great Turke.</p>
            <p>In this manner entering into the firſt gate of the <hi>Serralio, Siaus Baſſa</hi> left the Ambaſſadour, and rode forward before him to certifie the <hi>Baſſas</hi> of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. In this firſt Gate there ſtood about <hi>60. Capit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> or great Turkes Porters, with their Captaine, for a watch. Then approching to the ſecond gate of the <hi>Serralio,</hi> the Ambaſſadour lighted from his horſe, and was led in thereat by the arme, by <hi>Peichijs Baſſa,</hi> principal of the Pages, apparelled all in gold, whoſe office is to conduct all Ambaſſadours vnto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the great Turke: before this Gate there ſtood about <hi>100. Capitſers,</hi> with <hi>4.</hi> Captaines for a Guard, &amp; within the gate, were about <hi>300. Soubaſſas,</hi> which are Captaines of the <hi>Ianitſaries,</hi> each hauing a long white feather, like a Peacocks feather, on their heads. There all the <hi>Baſſas</hi> lighted off from their horſes, and went on foote to the <hi>Diuano</hi> (which is the Counſell-Chamber) wherein all the <hi>Baſſas,</hi> with the principall <hi>Viſier</hi> (repreſenting the great Turkes Perſon) foure dayes euery weeke giue open audience to all ſutors, and determine all cauſes of the whole Empyre.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18145:3"/>
            <p>Hauing paſt through this Gate, on the one ſide of two long Galleries, ſupported with Marble Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, there ſtood <hi>Ianitſarie Aga,</hi> the chiefe Commander of all the <hi>Ianitſaries,</hi> and of all the foot-men of Turky, with <hi>10000. Ianitſaries:</hi> and on the other ſide, <hi>Saphiler Agas,</hi> the chiefe Commander of the horſe-men, with <hi>2000. Saphers,</hi> or horſemen, who altogether bowing downe their heads after the Turkiſh manner, with great reuerence, ſaluted the Ambaſſadour, he doing the like vnto them. There met him the <hi>Kihaia,</hi> or Commander of all the <hi>Capitſers,</hi> and <hi>Siaus Baſſa,</hi> both of them being great Perſonages: they two led him into the <hi>Diuano,</hi> going before him with two long ſtaues or wands of ſiluer and gilt ouer, richly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled in cloath of Gold, which is the greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that can there be done to any man in the great Turkes Court.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Diuano</hi> ſate the <hi>Cahimachan,</hi> with all the <hi>Veſier Baſſas,</hi> who are chiefe and principall Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to the great Turke. Oppoſite ouer againſt the <hi>Cahimachan,</hi> there was a ſtoole ſet for the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. On his right ſide (which by the Turkes is held to be the vnworthieſt, as being vnder the ſword of another) ſate <hi>Mahomet Baſſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Admirall of Turky, betrothed to the great Turkes eldeſt Daughter, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hut Baſſa,</hi> marryed to the great Turkes Aunt, <hi>Ioſeph Baſſa, Chelil Baſſa,</hi> and <hi>Niſchanzi Baſſa,</hi> marryed to the great Turkes Niece, whoſe office is to ſet the great Turkes name to all Letters Pattents, and publike Inſtruments that are granted and ſent out by him. On the other ſide of <hi>Cahimachan</hi> (a reſonable or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſpace being left) ſate the two <hi>Cadileſchers,</hi> or chiefe Iudges of the whole Realme of Turky, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18145:3"/> on a ſeate alone the great <hi>Treaſoror,</hi> being a <hi>Veſier</hi> alſo. Ouer againſt him, in a chamber, apart, there ſate about <hi>300.</hi> Secretaries or Clarkes of the Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory, each of them being Auditors of a ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and vnder them their Clarkes.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadour hauing for a while ſpoken and conferred with the <hi>Baſſas,</hi> there was foure round ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tables brought in whereof one was ſet between the Ambaſſadour and the <hi>Cahimachan</hi> the ſecond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other <hi>Baſſas:</hi> the third before the <hi>Cadileſchers</hi> and the <hi>Treaſoror,</hi> and the fourth before the <hi>Niſchanzi Baſſa</hi> and his company: and there they were feaſted in ſumptuous manner, with many ſorts of meate, ſerued in great porceline diſhes, ſetting but one diſh downe at once after the Dutch manner. The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour eating with the <hi>Cahimachan,</hi> Captaine <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and <hi>Dahut Baſſa.</hi> In the middle of dinner, each of the <hi>Baſſas,</hi> and the Ambaſſadour dranke <hi>Sorbetta,</hi> in diſhes of gold, which is a kinde of drinke made of Water, Suger, and iuyce of Lemonds, mixed with Amber and Muſke: whereof they dranke but once, &amp; no more: for the Turkes are very ſober drinkers, and the great Lords vſe to drinke no wine. The <hi>Mutpac Emini,</hi> or the great Turkes chiefe Cooke, hauing vnder him aboue <hi>2000.</hi> Cookes and officers in the Kitchin, ſtood to ſerue at the table, and below him ſtood about <hi>100. Teſchnegers,</hi> or waiters, all with Caſſockes of cloath of golde, ſetting the meate vpon the tables, and ſeruing at them. Of them the <hi>Beies,</hi> that is the Gouernors of townes, and Barons are made.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cahimachan</hi> gaue the Ambaſſadour the firſt cut of euery diſh of meate, meane time the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18145:4"/> many precious Stones, all the Chamber being han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged about with moſt coſtly Hangings, embrodered and imboſſed with Gold, the ground being Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Veluet: the top thereof framed like a round tabernacle, all couered ouer with Golde, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers kindes of workes therein: this Chamber (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not very great) (when it is decked and hanged richly for to giue audience to any Ambaſſadour) is eſteemed and valued to be worth tenne hundred thouſand Hungarian Duckets, in Engliſh money, at ſeauen ſhillings a Ducket, <hi>350000</hi> pounds.</p>
            <p>When the Ambaſſadour came before the great Turke, one of the <hi>Capitſer Baſſas</hi> tooke vp the ſkirt of the Turkes Gowne, which the Ambaſſadour ſtooping downe, kiſt: and then hauing done the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed reuerence vnto his Maieſtie, two of the <hi>Capitſer Baſſas</hi> led him backward to the ſide of the Chamber, where in the ſide of the wall there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e furniſhed with rich Hangings and Cuſhins, but it is not the manner that any Ambaſſadour doth ſit downe in the Turkes preſence. The two <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitſer Baſſas</hi> ſtood ſtill by the Ambaſſadour, then the <hi>Dragoman</hi> was led before the great Turke, and brought backeward againe by the Ambaſſadour, and after them the twelue Gentlemen orderly one after another: that done, the firſt <hi>Viſier</hi> or <hi>Cahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan,</hi> read a Petition before the great Turke, thereby briefly beſeeching his Maieſtie, gratiouſly to vouchſafe audience vnto the Ambaſſadour.</p>
            <p>After that, the Ambaſſadour made an Oration in Latine, which by the <hi>Dragoman</hi> was preſently interpreted in Turkiſh ſpeech: and to when the Ambaſſadour had deliuered his Letters of credit,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18145:4"/> together with the propoſitions afore-ſaid in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a Bag of cloath of gold, according to their accuſtomed manner, by his Interpreter, to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himachan,</hi> he was led out of the Chamber againe, doing the accuſtomed honour and reuerence vnto the great Turke, going backewards as afore-ſaid, without any anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m he Turke himſelfe, or any of his <hi>Baſſas,</hi> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not their manner nor cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to doe it: and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> went out with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Courtiers and Officers, vntill he came out of the gate aforeſaid, on both ſides ſaluting <hi>Ianitſer Aga,</hi> and <hi>Saphiler Aga,</hi> being by them, and the <hi>Ianit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> and <hi>Saphilers</hi> likewiſe ſaluted as before. It is to be wondered at, that in the Turkes Court, when they ſit in Counſell which is ordinarily foure dayes in a weeke, there aſſembleth at the leaſt <hi>30000.</hi> men, all in pay and wages vnder the great Turke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Baſſas,</hi> who ſtand there ſo quietly, and with ſo great ſilence, that in a manner they ſhew to be ſo many Images, without life or ſoule.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadour with his traine, being on horſe-backe againe, they were led a little aſide (as the manner in that Country is) to ſee the Court and traine of the great Turke paſſe along before them, partly to honour the Ambaſſadours, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew the great Turkes Power. And firſt, all the <hi>Ianitſaries</hi> about <hi>10000.</hi> in number, with a great noyſe came out of the gate, and marcht before him, well apparelled, but without weapons. Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>500 Solachijs,</hi> or <hi>Bulucbaſſis,</hi> which are Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals and other Officers of the <hi>Ianitſaries:</hi> then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>500 Soubaſſis,</hi> with long white feathers vpon their heads, which are Captaines among others.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18145:5"/> Then on Horſe-backe followed <hi>Stampol Aga,</hi> being the chiefe of all the <hi>Samoglanes,</hi> which are certaine young men and Children, which are giuen to the great Turke tribute: then the <hi>Perchimalgis, Ianigſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Iagiſchijs,</hi> the Clarke of the <hi>Ianitſaries: Solach Baſſas,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Solachijs: Tagerſchij Baſſa,</hi> chiefe Hunter to the great Turke: the <hi>Chahagraby,</hi> or Lieutenant to <hi>Ianitſer Aga,</hi> and his Subſtitute. Then on foote followed <hi>200. Soubaſſis,</hi> and then <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitſer Aga</hi> himſelfe, Commander ouer all the <hi>Ianitſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi> after him followed <hi>100. Menegeſians,</hi> all with Girdles of Siluer about one of their hands, which alſo are <hi>Ianitſaries,</hi> and each of them carry a Torch before the <hi>Aga,</hi> when hee goeth the round by night through <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as all the great <hi>Viſiers</hi> and <hi>Baſſas</hi> night by night are bound in perſon to goe the round, to preuent an ſuch as ſeeke to doe any hurt or miſchiefe, each of them hauing an Executioner with them, to puniſh all thoſe that they finde doing any hurt or wickedneſſe, or that are in the ſtreetes, according to the deſert and merit of their offences, eyther by preſent death or otherwiſe. All the great Turkes Court hauing in this manner paſſed along before the Ambaſſadour; hee was againe conducted vnto his Lodging as aforeſaid, and for a further ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, there was by the <hi>Baſſas</hi> ſent vnto him, two <hi>Pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chijs,</hi> or Pages, belonging to the great Turke, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſiluer and gilt Hats whereof there are alwayes a great many going about the great Turkes Horſe, who although they are not accuſtomed to waite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other man, no not vpon the great <hi>Viſier Baſſa,</hi> yet they followed the Ambaſſadour, on eyther ſide of him as hee was on horſe-backe, till hee came to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18145:5"/> his Lodging. For this Amitie and Friendſhip made betweene the great Turke and the vnited <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> all the Turkes in generall much reioyced, ſo that as then it ſeemed to be a day of triumph, and from that time forward when the ſaid League was firſt begunne to be made, they beganne to treate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the releaſing of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> out of captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as alſo touching negotiation and traffique, to the which and, now already commandement is ſent by the great Turke into <hi>Barbary,</hi> and other places, to declare the Peace made betweene the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and the ſaid great Turke, and to command them, that from thence forth the <hi>Netherlands</hi> ſhall by them be holden and eſteemed to be his Friends. This Treatie with the great Turke (for the which the Lord be praiſed) concluded and agreed vpon, with the greateſt honour and reputation of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> that may be deuiſed, being made and ſigned with the great Turkes owne hand, and with his Oath thereunto annexed, was deliuered vnto the Ambaſſadour, vpon the ſixteenth day of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt paſt, being by him before for the ſpace of ſixe dayes peruſed, read, and in all defectiue places corrected and amended, in the preſence of certaine men that vnderſtood the Turkiſh Language, and were reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted thereunto by the ſaid Ambaſſadour.</p>
            <p>By which meanes the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the beſt and ſureſt Priuiledges in Turky, that euer heretofore haue to any Nation beene granted: for whatſoeuer the <hi>French-men, Engliſh-men,</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitians</hi> in generall, or any of them in particular, by the Turkes ſpeciall fauour and grace, haue obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him, it is all ſpecially ſet downe in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18145:6"/> 
               <hi>amitie and friendſhip, were preſented vnto Vs. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and ſubſtance whereof were, that vnderſtanding the Maieſticalneſſe of Our Royall and Princely State, you were moued and incited to ſeeke for Our intire Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and good will: and to ſhew your great deſires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, haue endeuoured your ſelues to the ſame end to write vnto Vs, and to make an Accord and Friendſhip with Vs, which might alwayes be holden and obſerued, declaring that your wils and deſires haue alwayes beene good and great in that reſpect, to ſeeke and craue Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at Our Imperiall hands; and to ſhew and declare your good affections vnto Vs in like ſort, and in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as other Kings haue done, which with Vs haue entered into League and Friendſhip; deſiring to be holden and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted among the numher of thoſe Kings that are Our Friends: and that Wee would grant vnto you Our Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of agreement and conſent therein, in ſuch manner as Wee haue giuen the ſame to other Kings of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Which that it may be done with ſinceritie and truth, together with other things which you further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and require at Our hands; (whereof the Contents being imparted vnto Our Royall Councill, and hauing fully and wholy vnderſtood your wils and meanings) We ef our Imperiall Grace and Fauour haue abundantly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and giuen vnto you by Our Letters Pattents, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame Priuiledges and Liberties which Wee haue in times paſt imparted to the Kings afore-ſaid, according to your owne deſires, but ouer and beſides the ſame, much more then you eyther haue ſought or deſired by your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Vs, which with Our owne hands, Wee haue by Our Letters Pattens confirmed, and giuen commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Our Maieſtie, that in all places and Countries of Our Empyre, wherein any of your Country-men and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18145:6"/> Subiects ſhall be knowne and found to be Slaues they ſhall be freely ſet at libertie, according to the Contents of Our ſaid Letters Pattents of Amitie, Peace, and Friendſhip. Further Wee giue you to vnderſtand, that your afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Ambaſſadour hath with great honour and modeſtie, as alſo with great care and diligence, performed and done his dutie and ſeruice in his ſaid Ambaſſage whereof hee was ſent by you, in all things hauing obtained the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Our Friendſhip; and in good manner and faſhion hath performed the ſame: and when he came before Vs, was permitted by word of mouth to ſpeake and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Meſſage and Commiſſion by you giuen vnto him, to be deliuered vnto Vs, which Wee hauing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as alſo well liked, allowed, and accepted of, together with the Preſents by you ſent, and deliuered by him vnto Vs, (and which We will keepe in Our owne preſence and continuall ſight) hauing receiued the ſame, as alſo the ſaid Ambaſſadour, with great Loue and Friendſhip. The auncient cuſtome of Our Maieſtie is, that all Our gates of grace, fauour, and good will, ſhall ſtand continually open for all, and vnto all men, and at all times; but eſpecially to thoſe that come vnto Vs with ſo great a deſire of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Friendſhip, to whom it is requiſite to ſhew and impart all honour and good will that poſſible may be. Therefore Wee ſay, that you hauing receiued theſe Our Letters, from thence-forth (as it is requiſite) Wee looke and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that you ſhall hold and obſerue the Treatie and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip made by you with Vs, perpetually; according to your owne Letters and Offers ſent vnto Vs, and in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme, as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> Our Friends, long time vnto this day haue held and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the like Friendſhip and Amitie. Which Wee hope you will doe in all points according to your Promiſes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18145:7"/> and that our Friendſhip may continue and hold firme and ſtable, Our deſire is that you ſhould from time to time eertifie vs, by Letters, of your eſtates and healths, and Wee for Our part, will not faile to fulfill and accompliſh all whatſoeuer ſhall tend vnto your good and welfare, with all fauour and grace, as neare as Wee can: and promiſe you further, that our good will and friendſhip ſhall not ceaſe continually to encreaſe towards you, for your good, and from good to better; whereof We would not haue you to doubt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in the middle of the Month of</hi> Gematil Elebla, <hi>in the yeare</hi> 1021 <hi>in the Imperiall Citie of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople; <hi>which GOD preſerue from all hurt and misfortune.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18145:7"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter, ſent by the Noble Lord <hi>Cahimachan,</hi> called <hi>Mahomet Baſſa,</hi> Commiſſarie generall of Turkie, dated (according <hi>to the Calculation of Chriſtendome) in the</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Month of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1612.</head>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="superscription">
               <body>
                  <head>THE SVPERSCRIPTION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Honour and greatneſſe of Chriſtendome, Princes of the great Gouernment of the Law of the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of the ſtate of the people of Chriſtendome, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of curteſie, and of the Honour and Power of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; The Lords and States generall of the vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of the</hi> Netherlands, <hi>and of all other places ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto them a good end, and the Grace and Fauour of</hi> GOD.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the Friendſhip which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to be ſhewed vnto Lords of your degree, and the accuſtomed fauour and amitie, of the great and mightie Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Turkie, which at this time is giuen and granted vnto your Honours; In ſigne of loue, and aſſurance of Friendſhip, I giue you to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the grace and helpe of God almightie (whom I beſeech to preſerue and defend the King, and by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and power of our holy Prophet, who is in glory, and reſteth in peace with God, protect and ſaue the King of all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18145:8"/> Lands and Seas; Dominator from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt; Commander ouer <hi>Mecha</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> the moſt Noble Prince of the whole Common-wealth of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiter of the World with grace and fauour; the moſt righteous King, whom GOD long proſper and preſerue vpon earth, his Kingdome and Greatneſſe with Honour, who therein is an vpholder in pouertie and miſerie of all creatures, the refuge of all poore oppreſſed people, an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancer of the Banner of the holy Law; King of <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> Dominator ouer the moſt mightieſt Monarchie in the World; Vpholder by the power of God, wherein he is King, of all Kings; and who hath his truſt and confidence in the fauour and promiſe of the true and onely GOD; the great and moſt puiſſant Emperour, our gratious and mightie King, <hi>Sultan Achomat Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m;</hi> Protecter of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran,</hi> whom GOD Almightie preſerue and maintaine in all power and Imperiall Maieſtie, and ſuffer him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ouer the whole world for his welfare and good, &amp;c.) that there was brought vnto his Imperiall Palace, (which is the vpholding and preſeruation of Honour, and the light of the world, ſhining aboue all the Powers and Maieſties of Kings) a Letter, ſignifying your great and kinde Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is, by your Ambaſſadour, CORNELIVS HAHA, one of the chiefe Commanders amongſt you, in the Law of Chriſtendome, and of Noble bloud (whoſe Honour God long preſerue) who being arriued in this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Palace, hath declared and fully ſignified your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours great good wils and meanings, as alſo the entire affections, which your ſaid Honours beare vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. VVhich done, your ſaid Ambaſſadour tooke his reſt for certaine dayes, after his long, weary, and troubleſome iourney, as being not well at eaſe, and after certaine daies of reſt, communicated his intent vnto mee, thereby to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18145:8"/> giue mee to vnderſtand the effect and meaning of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, according to your Commiſſion: to whom, in the behalfe of our great Emperour, wee ſhewed that fauour, reſpect and honour which hee well merited and deſerued; and therewithall tooke a true Copie of your Honors Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hauing imparted the ſame vnto the Lords, <hi>Viſiers</hi> of this Councill, ſuch as deale in matters of State, as alſo vnto thoſe that are wiſe and learned in the holy Law; and hauing conferred, and conſidered about the Contents, and of the heartie and good affection by you therein ſhewed vnto his Imperiall Maieſtie, being the mirrour and cleare light of the world (whoſe Noble Perſon, and puiſant Dominions God preſerue and keepe from all troubles and aduerſities which daily happen throughout the world) And finding your requeſt to be good and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſonable, as ſoone as wee were enformed of your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and deſires, wee delayed no time to impart the ſame vnto his Imperiall Maieſtie, who liking well, and allowing thereof, gaue commandement that all due and reſpectiue order ſhould ſpeedily be taken about the ſame, and that it ſhould be brought to good effect, with all diligence and care; and therewithall order was preſently taken <hi>ex motu proprio</hi> from the Emperour mouth and by his owne conſent, that your Ambaſſadour ſhould come vnto his Princely Palace and Preſence, to ſalute his Maieſtie, and thereupon your Honours ſaid Ambaſſadour, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and attended vpon in ſuch order as was fitting and conuenient for his Honour, hauing humbly ſaluted his Maieſtie, and being apparelled, both himſelfe and his Traine, with honourable Sutes, according to the manner and cuſtome of this Country; and that Honour and due reſpect ſhewed vnto him, which to his place and perſon was requiſite to be done: his Imperiall Maieſtie gaue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18145:9"/> licenſe and free permiſſion vnto him, to haue acceſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Court, for the execution of his Ambaſſage, as other Ambaſſadours and Gouernours of the Empyre vſe to doe, as alſo to conſult with the Lords <hi>Viſiers,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of the Law, and ſpecially the chiefe Iudge of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie, which is a Lord of the holy <hi>Mufti Effendi,</hi> together with the Lords <hi>Cadi Eſquieri</hi> (ſo the great men of the Land are named) and withall other his Gouernours about the ſame, and with his Maieſties aduice and conſent, your motion of Amitie and Friendſhip ſought and propounded vnto him, being well conſidered and aduiſed of by them, and they hauing fully and wholy declared the ſame vnto the great Monarch of the World, and the moſt mighty and vprighteſt King thereof (whom God preſerue) by the helpe and aſſiſtance of God: his Maieſtie freely and thankefully accepted of your good wils and Friendſhips, and hath placed the ſame among the number of thoſe that are vnited vnto him in perfect Amitie and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and hath determined and ordained that the ſame ſhall for euer be reſpected and maintained by him. And therewithall his Imperiall Maieſtie hath commanded that wee ſhould ſet downe and record the Articles of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vnite on both parts, according to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and alſo to make and ſend you a Letter in his owne Name.</p>
            <p>And I alſo for my part, as your good friend, haue written this Letter; which, with his Maieſties, wee ſend vnto your Honours, wiſhing that by Gods grace, and in an happy and proſperous houre, the perfect Amitie and Friendſhip knit betweene vs, may in like ſort long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, which with all my heart I deſire: for it is moſt ſure and certaine that the ſupreame Lord of the noble houſe of <hi>Ottomans,</hi> and the Imperator of all other Rulers and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18145:9"/> Lords in the World, our moſt Puiſant Lord and King, is ſo truely vnited in faſt and firme Friendſhip with your Honours, that from henceforth all the Fauours and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that may proceede and be imparted from his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall hands, vnto his Friends and Well-willers, ſhall be giuen and ſhewed vnto you, as by the Capitulation and agreement ſet downe and recorded he hath fully ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted and recorded, in ſuch manner that all promiſes, and conditions, made and ſpecified to be graunted vnto on his behalfe, within his Kingdomes and Dominions, ſhall be truely and faithfully obſerued, fulfilled and kept. And my ſelfe your good friend, in like manner, will not faile to ſhew you all the honour and reſpect that may be, and will by no meanes endure that the leaſt hurt or wrong whatſoeuer, ſhall be done vnto your Honours, (in your Subiects or Vaſſals) within theſe our Countries, for that the Word and Promiſe of our moſt righteous and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable King, (whom God preſerue) is for euer firme and ſtable, and moſt powerfull, in regard that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties minde hath beene, and is alwayes addicted vnto peace and quietneſſe, and ſpecially deſireth that his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould liue in vnitie and peace, that vnder the ſhadow of his Imperiall Maieſtie, they may ſo liue happily and at hearts eaſe. And ſeeing that the Lord of all the world hath granted you ſo great fauour and happy fortune to be vnited and ioyned in friendſhip, loue, and amitie with ſo puiſant great and magnanimious a King, repleniſhed with benignitie, grace, mercy, and compaſſion, as our Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is: It is moſt certaine, and you may aſſure your ſelues thereof, that his Commandements and promiſes are firme and moſt ſure, and that there ſhall be no contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie found therein, and aſſure your ſelues for certaine, that it ſhall not faile in any manner in regard that his
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18145:10"/> be a meanes to procure the welfare of all Gods creatures, to their euerlaſting benefit and good. Wee for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſay, that if on our ſide, all the Articles of agreement and Amitie, ſet downe and ſpecified in the Treatie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning vs, and alſo all that which on your ſides is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, concerning the peace, in your Letters, be well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, maintained, and kept, according to the inward and affectionate friendſhip ſhewed and proffered by you with heart and good will; that ſo in time to come, all our affaires may the longer and the better haue good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſſe, wee hope and truſt in GOD that in all the parts of the World, where Kings and Princes raigne, and ſhall heare and vnderſtand of the Friendſhip and Peace made betweene vs, thoſe that are our Friends will reioyce thereat, and ſuch as with-ſtand the ſame ſhall feele the ſmart thereof. God bring this our proceeding to good end, and for your good and proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Concerning your Ambaſſadour afore-ſaid, whom wee muſt commend, we ſay, that not onely touching his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, but alſo in all the reſt of the things belonging to matter of Eſtate, both in generall and perticular, hee hath done and performed the ſame with as much care and diligence as in him poſſible was, ſparing no labour, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, nor care, neyther in place nor matter, nor in any of his proceedings omitted any thing whatſoeuer, which he knew, or by any meanes perceiued, to be needfull or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to be propounded or moued, to bring theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to a good end. And ſpecially comming into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our moſt Puiſant Emperour, (whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) hee appeared there before him, with ſuch honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble behauiour, grace, and curteſie, that it pleaſed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie exceeding well, and moued him thereby to take great pleaſure and contentment in him: and in all his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18145:10"/> actions hath ſo behaued himſelfe, that more could not haue beene done, not required at his hands concerning his charge. And to conclude, ſuch a perſonage as hee (in the Superlatiue degree,) is fit to be an Ambaſſadour: in ſuch ſort, that all the Lord <hi>Viſiers,</hi> my fellowes, and the reſt of the Lords of the Emperours Court wondred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, and ſaid that ſuch a man that ſhould deale in publike affaires, ought to be ſuch a one, as he ſhewed himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs to be: being altogether in great admiration to ſee his manner of proceedings in all his affaires, and for that cauſe, being ſo well pleaſed and contented with his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, were well content that hee ſhould haue daily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto his Maieſties Court. Your Honours ſhall doe well to eſteeme much of him, for that a man of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts and qualities meriteth to be preferred.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing at this time, no more to ſay (hauing made a true relation of all that hath here beene done and paſt) but onely to wiſh health and long proſperitie vnto your Honours: wee leaue to trouble you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in the beginning of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> Giamati Elebla, <hi>in the yeare</hi> 1021. <hi>in the Citie of</hi> Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>which GOD preſerue.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18145:11"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter, written by the Lord <hi>Mufti Effendi,</hi> chiefe Iudge of the Turkiſh Empire: vnto the generall States <hi>of the vnited Prouinces of the</hi> NETHERLANDS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Viſant Lords of the Chriſtian Law, and the honour of the Nations vnder the MESSIAS; my Lords, the generall ſtates of the vnited <hi>Netherland</hi>-Prouinces, and moſt Noble Lord Prince MAVRICE: May it pleaſe you to vnderſtand, that this yeere was ſent vnto the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Palace of the moſt Puiſant King, highly magnified and exalted; the Executioner of the Commandements giuen to the World in the Temples; the furtherer of Iuſtice, and the Vpholder or Reſtorer of Townes and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the greateſt and mightieſt King and Monarch of the World (whoſe honour I beſeech God alwayes to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and that his Kingdome may flowriſh vntill the day of doome) your Honours Letters and Ambaſſadour, to treate of Amitie and Peace, with great reuerence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto the high Court of his Maieſties Dominions; wherein your Honours haue done a thing worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, and exceeding well accepted of, for that all thoſe that deſire to make Friendſhip, and to haue Peace with the King of the Noble Houſe of OTTOMAN (whom God encreaſe in Honour, Power, and Maieſtie vnto the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18145:11"/> Worlds end) vntill this day haue not by any meanes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured any loſſe or hinderance whatſoeuer, but haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by attained to great profit and aduantage, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly knowne vnto all the World, and among all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all thoſe vnto whom, or with whom, the moſt Puiſant King (whom God preſerue) doth make peace and contracteth Amitie, or that for their parts doe endeuour themſelues to obſerue and hold peace and Friendſhip with him, haue well experienced and tryed his great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, to whom his Maieſtie hath continually doubled, and ſhewed his ſpeciall grace and benignitie, which is a certaine ſigne and token, that in time to come, your Friendſhip proffered and obtained, ſhall more and more increaſe, and be ſo well ratified and eſtabliſhed, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whatſoeuer ſhall be cauſe to breake or infringe the ſame. For that the great Turke will ſhew your Honours ſuch friendſhip, that in his Empire of Turky neyther you, nor any of your Ships, ſhall neede to feare any hurt or harme to be done vnto you in any thing whatſoeuer. To conclude, wee all together will continue your perfect friends, and be friends to your friends, and foes to your foes: and the further that you proceede therein, ſo much the more ſhall the benefit of his Maieſties fauours be ſeene, and your aduantage procured thereby, and in this matter which by you hath beene ſought, all fauour and Friendſhip afford vnto you, although that in this point it is not vnknowne vnto you, how many aduerſaries you haue had, who by all meanes and wayes poſſible, haue ſought to hinder your proceedings herein, and to diuert it, that it might take no effect.</p>
            <p>Therefore as I haue ſaid, ſeeing that your enemies haue wrought thus ſecretly againſt you, it is great reaſon, that this League and Contract ſhould be ſurely made, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18145:12"/> to your Letters, the Articles haue beene ſet downe, certifying you, that all ſhall be done as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: and with all wee thinke that it was great reaſon that this peace ſhould be eſtabliſhed, and therefore our moſt puiſant Emperour hath beene content gratiouſly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of your Friendſhip, and according to your Letters, the afore-ſaid Priuiledges haue beene granted vnto vs: and that in all things whatſoeuer paſt concerning them, there hath nothing beene omitted that was requiſite to be put in according to your deſires. And for your Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour <hi>Cornelius Haga,</hi> whom your Honours ſent hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee hath performed his charge in that reſpect (in the Superlatiue degree:) and with great grace and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour gone through therewith, and hath executed the ſame with as much diligence as poſſible he might. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt needes ſay, that ſuch a man as he is, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth as well to be made an Ambaſſadour, as any one whatſoeuer of his degree, being of that Iudgement that hee is: the reaſon is, for that whatſoeuer hee hath done concerning this buſineſſe of yours, hee hath done it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, and therefore it is requiſite, that you take care, that no ſcandall may hereafter be procured thereby vnto you, and before all things to doe your endeuours that this Peace may continue firme and ſtable, for that it is euery way profitable and good for your Honours, and your townes. And vpon condition that your Honors ſhall keepe and firmely hold this Treatie, wee alſo will endeuour our ſelues to maintaine and vphold the ſame for euer: for our great and moſt Puiſant Emperour (whom God preſerue) is a courteous Prince, and exceeding gratious, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the grace and fauour that he can vnto his friends, being an Emperour of great Honour and Maieſtie, whoſe cuſtome is alwayes to doe well.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18145:12"/>
            <p>The Concluſion therefore of our Letter is, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath beene concluded touching this peace, you will take care to performe it to your powers. <hi>Moſes Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalmi</hi> a Iew, hath beene a great furtherer of your affaires, as much as in him lay, and hath made mee acquainted with all your proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace be with you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subscription">
               <body>
                  <head>THE SVBSCRIPTION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By him that executeth the Commandements that are ſent forth to be done for the honor and authoritie of the Puiſant and moſt Princely houſe of</hi> Ottomans, Mehemet <hi>the Sonne of</hi> G. Saalteldin. God haue mercy vpon vs all.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18145:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18145:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
